Sydor Rey Papers
Sydor Rey Papers
1940-1969
Rey, Sydor.
1.0 linear ft.
Polish American poet and novelist. Collection includes correspondence, clippings, photographs, writings.
3298889
Biographical History
Sydor Rey (b. 1908) was a Polish-American Jewish novelist and poet. He studied at the Universities of Warsaw and Lvov, where he received master's degrees in law and political science. He practiced law for a time in Warsaw where he also became known for his writing and was a member of the literary group Przedmiescie (Suburbs). His first novel, Kropiwniki, was published in 1937. Shortly thereafter (1939) he came to the United States where his work often appeared in the Polish-American press and in the Polish press in London, particularly Wiadomosci Tygodnik. He published numerous novels, short story collections and poetry anthologies in Polish and in English translation and, later, he wrote in English for American publication.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Sydor Rey Papers consist of biographical material, correspondence, memorabilia and writing.
Biographical material contains a brief autobiographical sketch by Rey and information about the Wiadomosci Tygodnik (Weekly Magazine), a Polish-language newspaper published in London.
Correspondence consists of letters from Rey (most of these are to John S. Mayfield, former librarian at Syracuse University) and letters from others about Rey.
Memorabilia contains clippings about Rey, including one from the Syracuse University Daily Orange on the occasion of his donation of his papers, and a few black-and-white photographs of Rey and Mayfield.
Writings includes both published and typescript pieces. The vast majority of the published pieces are in issues of Wiadomosci Tygodnik and include letters to the editor, poems, excerpts from Rey's novels, and other items. Typescripts include poems and short pieces, some of which may eventually have been published. There is also one folder of miscellaneous lists of published pieces.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged within each series alphabetically, except for the Wiadomosci Tygodnik newspapers which are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Rey, Sydor.; Wiadomosci Tygodnik.; Authors, Polish -- 20th century.; Polish literature.; Polish poetry.; Polish-American poetry.; Polish-American literature.; Polish-American newspapers.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Typescripts.; Authors.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Sydor Rey, 1966.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous, typed autobiographical sketch by Rey; printout of information about Wiodomosci Tygodnik (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Rey, Sydor, 1940; 1943,; 1947-1948,; 1956-1960,; 1965-1968; majority are from Rey to John S. Mayfield (Box 1)
  - Others (about Rey), 1967-1969 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings, 1940; 1962,; 1965-1966; originals and photocopies; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1966; undated; of Rey alone, and several of Rey and Mayfield, taken in London (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Published items
    - Wiodomosci Tygodnik (Weekly Magazine), 1957-1967; poems, letters to the editor, essays, short stories; English title provided in parenthesis if known; 62 issues
      - [untitled], 6/16/1957; poem, with Rey's annotations (Oversize 1)
      - Anioł-Stróż (Angel of [?]), 10/6/1957; footnote says: Fragment z "Ksiegi rozbitków" (Oversize 1)
      - List (Letter), 12/22-29/57; poem (Oversize 1)
      - Mój mit (My myth), 2/16/1958; footnote says: Fragment z "Ksiegi rozbitków" (Oversize 1)
      - Nekrofilia (Necrophilia), 4/27/1958 (Oversize 1)
      - Felicja (Felicia), 7/13/1958 (Oversize 1)
      - Cisza (Silence), 7/20-27/58; poem (Oversize 1)
      - Pisarze emigracyjni a literatura Krakowa (Emigrant writers, literature of Krakow), 8/17/1958; only one paragraph of article is by Rey (Oversize 1)
      - Portret bez twarzy (Portrait without a face), 11/2/1958; lengthy article (Oversize 1)
      - Smutek (Sadness), 12/21-28/58; poem (Oversize 1)
      - Pasternak i Hemingway (Pasternak and Hemingway), 3/1/1959; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - Tyrzy fragmenty (Tyrzy fragment), 3/8/1959; footnote says: Fragment z "Ksiegi rozbitków" (Oversize 1)
      - Pierwszy Maja (First of May), 4/19/1959; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - Tyrzy Szkice (Sketch of Tyrzy?), 6/7/1959; footnote says: Fragment z "Ksiegi rozbitków" (Oversize 1)
      - Swiątkarz beskidzki, 6/14/1959; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - Przyjemniejszy szmer, 8/9/1959; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - [nothing by Rey], 10/11/1959 (Oversize 1)
      - Najcichszy Krok (Quietest step), 10/18/1959; poem (Oversize 1)
      - Pisarze nie zawodowi (Writers not professionals?), 11/15/1959; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - Odzyskane dzieciństwo (Recovered childhood), 1/31/1960 (Oversize 1)
      - Niebo jest moim domen (Heaven is my home), 2/28/1960; poem (Oversize 1)
      - Generał (General), 4/3/1960 (Oversize 1)
      - Na Pustyni (In a desert), 4/24/1960; poem (Oversize 1)
      - Miasto na Long Island (City on Long Island), 6/5/1960; poem (Oversize 1)
      - Ksiądz-Technik (Priest-Technician), 6/26/1960 (Oversize 1)
      - Cudotwórca (Miracle worker), 10/2/1960 (Oversize 1)
      - Jadłodajnia, 11/20/1960 (Oversize 1)
      - Bajka, 12/18-25/60; poem (Oversize 1)
      - Dobrzi sąsiedzi (Good neighbors), 1/29/1961; poem? Very short piece, quotes Dylan Thomas apparently (Oversize 1)
      - Nasz Stosunek do Twórczości Sienkiewicza, 2/12/1961; only 4 paras are by Rey; footnote says "por. Odpowiedzi Ferdynanda Goetla, …[lots of other names] w nr. Nr. 774 i 775 Wiadomości" (Oversize 1)
      - Pisarki (Female writers), 4/30/1961; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - Para mistrzów (Pair of masters), 5/14/1961; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - Fraszki (Epigrams) / Poezja Nierymowana (Unrhymed poetry) / Kłamca, 5/21/1961; very short, possibly quotations of others? (Oversize 1)
      - Cisza (Silence), 6/4/1961; Same page also includes lengthy piece by Vladimir Nabokov (Wladimir Nabokow) and Jerzy Tepa on Lolita, "Ostatnie Spotkanie" [??] (Oversize 1)
      - Balzac i Victor Hugo (Balzac and Victor Hugo), 9/3/1961; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - Ojce nasz (Our father) / Wioska po wojnie (Village after a war) / Banita (Exile), 12/24-31/61; three poems (Oversize 1)
      - Barabasz i Judasz (Barabbas and Judas), 1/21/1962; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - Konfident (Confidence), 3/25/1962; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - Deser czy Danie Głowne?, 4/8/1962; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - Krawiec Grzegorz (Tailor of Grzegorz), 5/20/1962; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - Polska szkola poetycka (Polish school of poetry), 6/17/1962; letter to the editor (Oversize 1)
      - Emilia i Antoni (Emily and Antony), 8/26/1962; footnote says "Fragment wiekszej całości" (Oversize 1)
      - Edmund (Edmund), 12/9/1962; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - Ofiara Radość (Victim? of Joy), 5/26/1963; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - Pearl, 6/23/1963 (Oversize 1)
      - [untitled], 7/21/1963; letter to the editor, begins "W związku z arytkułem Stanisława Irzyka…" Also includes issue #4 of "Na Antenie: mówi Rozgłośnia Polska Radia Wolna Europa" and front page article on election of Pope John XXIII (Oversize 1)
      - Pan własnego życia (Your? personal life), 7/28/1963 (Oversize 1)
      - Festyn (Gala) / Thorntonowi Wilderowi (Thornton Wilder), 9/15/1963; translation into Polish of poem by Thornton Wilder (Oversize 1)
      - Dwór, 1/26/1964; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - Całopalenie, 5/1/1964; poem (Oversize 1)
      - Śmierć nieuzasadniona (Unfounded? death), 5/10/1964; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - Pan i Sługa (You and the servant), 9/20/1964; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - Dysputa (Debate), 10/18/1964; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - Przytułek (Refuge), 11/15/1964; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - Salomon, nie Dawid (Solomon, not David), 2/14/1965; letter to the editor (dated from Paris) (Oversize 1)
      - Wariacje na temat śmierci, 6/6/1965; very long piece, spans 2 pages (Oversize 1)
      - Scena Miłosna, 7/11/1965; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi"; also includes issue #27/28 of "Na Antenie: mówi Rozgłośnia Polska Radia Wolna Europa" (Oversize 1)
      - Bankiet (Banquet), 8/22/1965; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - Swaty (Matchmaking), 10/10/1965; footnote says "Fragment powieści p.t. "Ludzie miejscowi" (Oversize 1)
      - [nothing by Rey], 1/9/1966 (Oversize 1)
      - Lekcja Historii (History lesson), 5/8/1966; only one sheet, pages 3-5 (Oversize 1)
      - Nowy tom wierszy Sydora Reya (New book of poems by Sydor Rey) / Mi ato? / Kraniec miasta (End of the city) / Smak słowa i śmierci / Raz kozie śmierć / Bestia (Beast) / Egzystencjalizm (Existentialism), 1/2/1967 (Oversize 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1929; 1940,; 1963; Polish and English, includes copy of Rey's first published piece in 1929 (Box 1)
  - Typescript
    - Earth (Box 1)
    - The general (Box 1)
    - Hitler's mother (Box 1)
    - Letter from the cashier (Box 1)
    - Nastia's cloth (Box 1)
    - Poems, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Portrait without a face (Box 1)
    - Shulim (Box 1)
    - Stella and Wasylcio (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, lists of published titles, notes (Box 1)